בוקר טוב Boker tov everybody. בוקר טוב, Boker tov, בוקר טוב. Boker
tov. Today's דף daf is דף מ. Daf Mem. We are, if
we are able to, if we are able to keep to the
pace, we will finish the first פרק perek today. So we pick
up at the bottom of ל"ט עמוד ב, Lamed-Tet Amud Bet, after
all of these משניות mishnayot categorizing מצוות. mitzvot. We had a משנה
mishna that says כל, kol, the thing was כל kol and מצוה,
mitzvah, and there was a little bit about ארץ eretz and חוץ
לארץ. chutz la'aretz. So then we had anybody who does a מצוה
mitzvah is נוחל את הארץ, nochal et ha'aretz, which means gets עולם
הבא olam ha-ba but also reaps the rewards in this world, okay?
And the גמרא Gemara dealt with that in contrast to the משנה
mishna in פאה Pe'ah that says only a specific set of מצוות
mitzvot do you reap the reward in this world, and came up
with interesting ways of framing it about somebody who has exactly fifty-fifty
מצוות ועבירות mitzvot ve'aveirot and so on, taking a little bit of
the power out of the משנה. mishna. But then we dealt with
the bigger question, which is, do you really reap the rewards of
מצוות mitzvot in this world? And the position—because there's a משנה mishna
that says that you experience the opposite, that you could be a—you
could have more merits and actually have a tragic life, and the
reverse: more, you know, more sins and actually have a very successful
life. So one answer was, well, some days will be tragic, some
days will be successful. So a way that God evens the accounts
and pays you back, but ultimately, broadly speaking, your life will be
in accordance to your deeds. That's the way תוספות Tosafot read it.
But then the גמרא Gemara says, no, maybe actually there's a major
theological debate here, and this is the position of רבי יעקב, Rabbi
Yaakov, who says, and this is the famous phrase of the גמרא,
Gemara, שכר מצוה בהאי עלמא ליכא. schar mitzvah be-hai alma leka. Reward
for a מצוה mitzvah in this world does not exist. Don't expect
to be rewarded for מצוות mitzvot in this world. All the promises
in the תורה Torah are promises for עולם הבא. olam ha-ba. That
is a way, a fundamental way of dealing with the challenge of
צדיק ורע לו. tzaddik ve'ra lo. Why do the good people suffer?
They'll be rewarded in עולם הבא. olam ha-ba. The promises of the
world are for עולם הבא. olam ha-ba. And that's as opposed to
our משנה mishna and the משנה mishna in פאה Pe'ah that say
you actually do get rewarded in this world for at least to
some degree for some of the מצוות. mitzvot. And the example the
גמרא Gemara had that made רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov articulate this position—famous
example is a kid who is listening to his father and he's
going and sending away the mother bird and getting the eggs or
getting the chicks and he's coming back on the ladder and he
falls and he dies. So he did two מצוות mitzvot that he's
promised long life and nevertheless, how do you explain this? And, you
know, the גמרא Gemara says, well, maybe it never happened. But okay,
the point is we all know such a thing could happen. And
as the גמרא Gemara says, the גמרא Gemara says that רבי יעקב
Rabbi Yaakov actually did experience it. I would more say that we
all know in our heart of hearts that such a thing could
very realistically happen. How would you explain it? So obviously we have
to say, take our experience of the real world and say that
the promises of the תורה Torah are really for עולם הבא. olam
ha-ba. That is רבי יעקב'ס Rabbi Yaakov's position, okay? And now the
גמרא Gemara is sort of going to continue with that. So let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara says like
this now,
by the way, the מהרש"א Maharsha says that that idea of רבי
יעקב Rabbi Yaakov can work for broadly based promises like והארכת ימים
למען ייטב לך. ve-ha'arachta yamim le-ma'an yitav lach. But what do you
do with all the ברכות brachos and the קללות klalos in the
תורה Torah which are very concrete and specific? You can't explain יככה
ה' בשחין ובקדחת yakecha Hashem bashechin uvakadachas or whatever is עולם הבא,
olam ha-ba, right? So what do you do with that? So the
מהרש"א Maharsha says, no, those are promises for when the entire ציבור
tzibur as a people, you know, are meritorious or are sinful, then
those—then those promises actually will happen. But it's not true at the
private—at the personal and private level. Right. So the challenge of שכר
ועונש, schar ve-onesh, of צדיק ורע לו, tzaddik ve'ra lo, is much—is
really much more pronounced at the individual level, not at the communal
level. Of course, you know, questions at the communal level have also
come up when there have been communal tragedies, you know, and most
of course recently, of course, the Holocaust. And how do you explain
that in any context of שכר ועונש? schar ve-onesh? But anyway, it's
important that the מהרש"א—we Maharsha are not having a discussion right now
about theology of the Holocaust, but the מהרש"א Maharsha at least tries
to situate the nature of the discussion in the גמרא. Gemara. Let's
take a look now as the גמרא Gemara says. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this: והא
אמר, ve-ha amar, okay, one minute... okay, והא
אמר רבי
אלעזר, ve-ha amar Rabbi Elazar, first of the middle-sized lines, end of
the lines. והא אמר רבי אלעזר, Ve-ha amar Rabbi Elazar, doesn't רבי
אלעזר Rabbi Elazar say שלוחי מצוה אינם ניזוקין? shluchei mitzvah einam nizokin?
People that are going to do a מצוה mitzvah are not injured
in their way. So it's like funny: well, we answered the תורה.
Torah. The תורה'ס Torah's talking about עולם הבא, olam ha-ba, okay? But
רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak says in a עולם הזה olam ha-zeh type
of a way that they're not—that they're not injured. So how do
you explain what happened to this kid? Right? So we have to—so
the גמרא Gemara says התם בהליכתן שאני. hatam be'halichatan shani. You gotta
love it. Like, okay, we explained away all of the promises in
the תורה, Torah, but now we have a statement that clearly was
meant in a very practical way: you're not injured in this world.
And so how does that work in with this theology? Or with
our experience of reality? So the גמרא Gemara says התם בהליכתן שאני.
hatam be'halichatan shani. No,
no, no. There it's different because there he wasn't doing the מצוה
mitzvah with the case of the kid sending away the mother bird.
It was—he was actually in the process of returning from the מצוה.
mitzvah. Going to and returning is different than doing the מצוה. mitzvah.
The גמרא Gemara says והא אמר רבי אלעזר שלוחי מצוה אינם ניזוקין
לא בהליכתן... ve-ha amar Rabbi Elazar shluchei mitzvah einam nizokin lo be'halichatan...
ולא בחזרתם, velo bachazirasom, but now he explicitly says that if you’re
doing a מצוה mitzvah you’re not injured on your way there and
your way back, even on your way there and your way back,
so how do you explain what happened? So the גמרא Gemara says
סולם רעועה הוה. sula ra'ua hava. No, no, no, the ladder was
a shaky ladder. דקביע היזיקא dekevia hezeika and therefore when there is
a fixed sort of risk danger there then doing a מצוה mitzvah
saves you from normal mishaps, saves you from things that are unwarranted
tragedy, unexpected. It doesn't protect you in terms of when you're really
when what you're doing is actually very risky on its own terms.
וכל היכא דקביע היזיקא לא סמכינן אניסא. vechol heicha dekevia hezeika lo
samchinan anisa. So the גמרא Gemara and anywhere I'm sorry read that
one. וכל היכא דקביע היזיקא לא סמכינן אניסא. vechol heicha dekevia hezeika
lo samchinan anisa.
So you will not be protected by a נס nes if there's
a fixed risk and danger. דכתיב ויאמר שמואל איך אלך ושמע שאול
והרגני. dechsiv vayomer Shmuel eich elech veshamah Shaul veharogani.
How will I go and שמואל Shmuel hear and he to anoint
דוד Dovid as king, שאול Shaul hear he will kill me. So
why didn't God say well you're שלוחי מצוה? shluchei mitzvah? God should
have quoted רב יצחק. Rav Yitzchak. So the point is this is
that or רבי אלעזר Rebbe Elozor excuse me not רב יצחק Rav
Yitzchak רבי אלעזר. Rebbe Elozor. Point is no קביע היזיקא שאני. kevia
hezeika shani. So רבי אלעזר Rebbe Elozor is saying is that doing
a מצוה mitzvah will protect you enough that unexpected bad things won't
happen to you. But as there's actual risks there it's not going
to create miracles to protect you from objective risks. Now of course
what you could also say about that
is that now I forgot what I was going to say. Yes
Michael you were going to say. Well I have a question on
that because I remember that other גמרא Gemara says מורא לא יעלה
על ראשו mora lo ya'aleh al rosho and here שמואל Shmuel is
clearly afraid of שאול. Shaul. Yeah it's a good question he presumably
you would also say I don't know it's a good question קביע
היזיקא kevia hezeika but I don't know. It doesn't mean that you
can be unrealistic about the real risks. I mean I think there's
a difference about being fearful of and just taking necessary precautions. But
anyway I'm not afraid I just
have to take the necessary precautions I'm not stupid either right? So
anyway but it's a good question. But anyway no but what I
was going to say is that it's interesting that once the גמרא
Gemara asserts this then that's also an answer to how did the
guy fall down from the ladder and the תורה Torah promised you
long life? The תורה's Torah's promise of long life is not when
you're negligent
and take undeserved risk. Right you can't say well the תורה Torah
promises me long life I'm going to go ahead
and skydive without a parachute. Right or whatever do anything that's untowardly
risky. Right and there's also not only is it that it requires
a miracle to save you there because it's a high risk but
there's also a sense of
negligence and that you exposed yourself to that risk. So it's interesting
that once the גמרא Gemara asserts that obviously it takes some of
the punch out of the need for the other statement. But anyway
moving on. The גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רב יוסף אלמלא
דרשה אחר להאי קרא כרבי יעקב בר ברתה לא חטא. Amar Rav
Yosef ilmalei darsha Acher lehai kra keRebbe Yaakov bar Barteh lo chata.
Had אחר Acher אלישע בן אבויה Elisha ben Abuya known how to
interpret this פסוק pasuk like רבי יעקב בר ברתה, Rebbe Yaakov bar
Barteh, right he would not have sinned. Okay 'cause he's basically isn't
ברתה Barteh the son of his daughter?
Yeah but I don't know I mean I think that's just that
was just it just said רבי יעקב אומר. Rebbe Yaakov omer. Before
just said רבי יעקב, Rebbe Yaakov, רבי יעקב אומר. Rebbe Yaakov omer.
Yeah. So he was a relative?
That is a good point.
I didn't pick up on that.
I didn't pick up on that. Do your notes say anything about
that? רבי יעקב Rebbe Yaakov son of his daughter it was his
grandson. Son of the daughter of
אחר. Acher. Okay I don't know that's I didn't pick up on
that. Anyway you could take a look. לא חטא lo chata he
would not have sinned. Because basically he's saying that this is way
of attributing although אחר's Acher's apostasy is attributed to different things right
in the famous discussion in חגיגה Chagigah it's attributed to נכנס לפרדס
nichnas lapardes and what he sort of saw up in
heaven but here it's attributing it obviously it's attributing to the fact
that he was he had some theological things that were theologically challenged
that did not that forced him to commit apostasy and that forced
him to reject the faith.
So you could try to be sort of say both are true
like he saw this vision and then it was reinforced by an
experience he had in the real world where it seems like there
was no justice in the real world or the reverse he had
this experience and that laid seeds of doubt and then he had
this vision but it's a different way of dealing with what led
to his apostasy and he basically is saying what led to his
apostasy was that he saw the promises of the תורה Torah blatantly
contradicted in the real world and he did not know how to
interpret this he either didn't know how to or was not satisfied
with this way of reinterpreting the verse. So the גמרא Gemara says
ואחר מאי הוא? ve’Acher mai hu? איכא דאמרי eika de’amri what
was the what did אחר Acher see? Some say כי האי גוונא
חזא ki hai gavna chaza he saw exactly this case a kid
being sent by the father etc. ואיכא דאמרי eika de’amri לישנא דחוצפית
המתורגמן חזא. lishna de’chutzpis hameturgeman chaza. No he saw the tongue of
חוצפית המתורגמן Chutzpis Hameturgeman one of the people that was martyred in
the time of what's it called. Hadrian, דהוה גרר ליה דבר אחר,
de-hava garer lei davar acher, that a pig was dragging it and
through like the dungheaps. ואמר ve-amar and he said, אחר אחר. Acher
Acher. Oh,
that's a good point, I didn't pick up on that. You're probably
right. דבר אחר. davar acher. Okay, אמר פה שהפיק מרגליות, amar peh
she-hefik margaliot, this, the, this mouth that pearls used to come out
of this mouth, ילחך עפר yelachech afar will now be licking the
dust? So how could this be? Where are all of God's promises,
you know, that the most righteous and the great people of תורה
Torah are treated this way? Obviously all those promises were, you know,
are all false and it led him to commit apostasy. נפק חטא,
nafaq chata, he went out and he sinned.
Okay, you had a hand up Tuvia? תוספות Tosafot says that this
means that רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov was the grandson of אחר, Acher,
that אחר Acher was his maternal grandfather. Interesting, so maybe that's also
like a nice sort of sense of a closure there. There it
is that his grandchild was sort of, was dealt, sort of struggled
with the same issue, right, but stayed in the fold and found
a way to reconcile it. Right, okay, yeah I just didn't pick
up on it. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this:
רמי, Rami, okay, so רמי בר טובי בר רב כסנא לרבא. Rami
bar Tuvia bar Rav Kisna le-Rava. So רמי בר טובי Rami bar
Tuvia showed a contradiction to רבא. Rava. תנן, Tnan, ארבעה שיש כל
עושה מצוה אחת מטיבין לו. arba'ah she-yesh kol oseh mitzvah achat metivim
lo. If you do one מצוה, mitzvah, it's good to you. עשה
אין לא עשה לא. assah in lo assah lo. Only doing is
it good to you and not being passive. רמיני, Ramini, I'll ask
you, ישב ולא עבר עבירה, yashav velo avar aveirah, we have a
ברייתא Baraita that says if you sit and you just passively don't
do an עבירה, aveirah, נותנין לו שכר כעושה מצוה, notnin lo sechar
ke-oseh mitzvah, you're rewarded like doing a מצוה. mitzvah. So all you
have to do is stay home all day, stay in bed, read
novels, and you get all these מצוות. mitzvot. So the גמרא Gemara
obviously demands an explanation. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר ליה לא
התם כגון שבאת דבר עבירה לידו וניצל הימנה. amar lei lo hatam
kegon she-ba'at davar aveirah leyado venitzal himena. No, no, no, that doesn't
mean you just passively did not choose to do an עבירה. aveirah.
That means that you were tempted and you found the strength to
resist the temptation. So the strength of resisting a temptation is not
just, hey, you didn't transgress. I mean, it's a powerful statement. It's
saying like, you know, that's the difference between a מצות עשה mitzvat
aseh and a מצות לא תעשה. mitzvat lo ta'aseh. It's like a
מצות לא תעשה mitzvat lo ta'aseh is you didn't do anything bad.
A מצות עשה mitzvat aseh is you did something good. So it
says, you know, most of the time that's true, like I didn't
choose right now to go to the McDonald's and to buy myself
a cheeseburger. יישר כח, yasher koach, I want to go to store,
I didn't do anything bad. But if I actually was tempted and
I found the strength to resist, that wasn't just not doing something
bad, that counts like a מצוה, mitzvah, that counts like I actually
did something good. Okay, כי הא, ki ha, now דבר עבירה davar
aveirah often very much also has a sexual connotation, so the
גמרא Gemara says כי הא דרב חנינא בר פפא, ki ha de-Rav
Chanina bar Pappa, תבעתה ההיא מטרוניתא, tavateih ha-hi matronisa, a certain matron,
a Roman woman sort of propositioned him for sex. אמר מילתא, amar
milta, he, and it was obviously there was a power differential there
on her side, so he, you know, it was hard for him
to resist or whatever, so אמר מילתא amar milta he said some
word, some like, you know, mystical word, ומלי נפשיה שיחנא וכיבי, umali
nafshi shichna ve-chivei, his body was filled with like boils and blisters
so he was repugnant, so she would leave him alone. עבדה היא
מילתא, avdah hi milta, ואיתסי, ve-itasi, but she also knew some powerful
mystical words, so she did something and he got healed. So what
was he going to do now? ערק טשא בההוא בי בני, arka
tasha behahu bei banei, he went and he hid in a certain
bathhouse דכי הוו עיילין בתרין אפילו ביממא הוו מתזקי. de-chi havi aylin
bitrein afilu biyemama havi mitzeki. You might remember this from another story
about somebody who went to a בי בני, bei banei, somebody lodged
in a בית מדרש Beit Midrash where even if two, that was
so dangerous, there were demons there that even if two people went
during the daytime they would be injured. So it was a haunted
bathhouse. Okay, but he was rather be there than expose himself to
this woman. למחר אמרו ליה רבנן, lemachar amru lei Rabbanan, and the
next day the rabbis said to him, מאי נטרך, mai natrach, who
protected you against the מזיקין mazikin when you were in that
bathhouse? אמר להו שני נושאי קיסר שמרוני כל הלילה, amar lehu shney
nusei keisar shamruni kol halaila, so whether he was just סתם stam
saying this or there were something that appeared like two of the
Caesar's, you know, like soldiers protected me over the night. אמרו ליה
amru lei they said to him, שמא דבר ערוה בא לידך וניצלת
הימנו, shema davar ervah ba leyadcha venitzalta himeno, maybe you were tempted
by a or at least, you know, by some by a sexual
sort of temptation and you were saved from it? דתנינא כל הבא
דבר ערוה לידו וניצל הימנו, de-tanyana kol haba davar ervah leyado venitzalta
himeno, anybody that has
the opportunity for sexual sin, the temptation for sexual sin is presented
and the man, person is able to resist it,
עושין לו נס, osin lo nes, a miracle is done to them,
and that of course is as we know is exactly what happened.
Okay, so now we're going to focus on that, on the power
of... right, I don't know if he did or he found out
next morning, but I mean the story is better if he knew
and he didn't care because he was willing to rather do that
than than expose himself to temptation. So now we're going to have
a couple of stories though of getting these sort of inner strength
and fortitude to resist temptation. Okay, it's quite interesting one has to
acknowledge because you know normally the man is always seen as the
initiator, the predator, you know, particularly and so on, and here it's...
It’s the woman who’s doing it and the man who’s resisting.
Yeah true, it’s like a יוסף Yosef story. But one also wonders
if it really is playing against the type because often it’s seen
that women are
easily, sort of, seduced, right? And although sometimes you have men that
are easily seduced, that whole story with what’s her name? Wasn’t that
whole story with ילתא Yalta and whatever?
Anyway, whatever, here it’s still like the men are the ones who
are able to withstand sexual temptation and so on. So let’s take
a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, גבורי כח עושי
דברו לשמוע בקול דברו, Gibborei koach osei devaro lishmoa bekol devaro, people
of great valor who do God’s words, who hear
the voice of God’s words, כגון רבי צדוק וחבריו, Kegon Rabbi Tzadok
vechaverav, like רבי צדוק Rabbi Tzadok and his colleagues. רבי צדוק Rabbi
Tzadok who had the power to resist temptation. רבי צדוק תבעה ההיא
מטרוניתא, Rabbi Tzadok teva’ah hahi matronita, a certain matron, Roman woman, seduced
him. גרוגרות? Grogrot? That might be. אמר לה, Amar lah,
and he said to her, חלש לי לבאי, Chalash li libbai, you
know what, I’m weak, my heart is weak. לא מצנינא, Lo matzinna,
I don’t have the strength to engage in sexual relations. איכא מידי
למיכל, Ika midi lemeichal, do you have something to eat? So he
was doing this basically to buy time or something. Now רש"י Rashi
points out again that there was a power differential here, that she
was a powerful woman probably reflected by the word מטרוניתא, Matronita, and
therefore like he might have felt that his life was at risk
if he resisted, so he was buying time rather than just saying
no.
So אמרה לה, Amrah lah, she said to him, איכא דבר טמא,
Ika davar tamei, yeah, we have some pork in the house, we
have some bacon.
So אמר לה, Amar lah, מאי נפקא מינה דעביד הא אכול הא,
Mai nafka mina de’avid ha achul ha, so like what difference does
it make? The one who does this will eat this.
Like if I’m sort of bemoaning, it sounds like his fate, that
if I’m going to have to now
give in to this sin, I’m going to be brought so low
that I’m going to have to actually sin in this other way
as well, being forced to eat חזיר Chazir and so on. Again
we have the
חזיר Chazir theme. שגרה תנורא, Shagra tanura, but anyway, so she said,
or also maybe he was making a point to her, like he
says, oh no, we do have some pork, but you’re a Jew,
you won’t eat pork, and he said, look, if you’re asking me
to do the same type of a violation with you, it’s the
same thing of a sin against my God. But it is true,
most people would probably feel there would be more of a violation
to eat pork than it would be to engage in a forbidden
sexual act, right? So she says, I’m not sure you want what
we have to eat, I only have some pork around. He says,
look, you know what, it’s like it’s the same type of a
sin, so trying maybe to have her appreciate, you know, how difficult
it was what she was demanding of him. But anyway, she said,
okay, as long as it’s the same sin, I’ll cook up the
pork.
So the גמרא Gemara says,
דעביד הא אכול הא, De’avid ha achul ha, שגרה תנורא, Shagra tanura,
she lit the oven. כמנחא
ליה, Kamancha leh, and was putting the pork on the oven. סליק
ויתיב בגווה, Salik veyativ begavah, in the oven, and he went and
he sat in it. So maybe that’s also why he said I
might as well have the pork so he could be able to
do this. So he jumped into the oven, he was willing to
commit suicide rather than submit to her. אמרה לה, Amrah lah, she
said to him, מאי האי, Mai hai, what’s going on here? אמר
לה, Amar lah, he said to her, דעביד הא נפיל בהא. De’avid
ha nafil beha. So this plays off of the this equals that.
He says, and if I do such a thing, sin, I will
fall into a
fire, I’ll get
גיהנם. Gehinnom. Okay, so therefore he appreciated
how weighty it was for him. אמרה לה, Amrah lah, she said
to him, אי ידעי כולי האי לא צערתיך, Ei yadei kulei hai
lo tza’artich, if I knew that it was so weighty for you,
I would have respected it more and I would not have caused
you this type of angst. Let me just read the other story.
רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, now that was one story, רבי צדוק, Rabbi
Tzadok, we said רבי צדוק Rabbi Tzadok and his colleagues. So here
is the next story. רב כהנא הוה קא מזבין דיקולי. Rav Kahana
hava ka mazbin dikulei. So רב כהנא Rav Kahana was selling wicker
baskets. תבעה מטרוניתא, Teva’ah matronita, a certain woman propositioned him, and also
he was in a difficult position to resist. אמר לה, Amar lah,
he said to her, איזיל איקשיט נפשאי, Izil ikashit nafshai, you know
what, let me go make myself look nice. Okay. סליק וקנפיל מאיגרא
לארעא. Salik vekanafil me’igra le’ara. So he went up to the roof
to escape, and he fell from the roof to the ground. Now
it sounds also like he actually jumped from the roof. It says
he fell, okay, but what else was he doing? He didn’t, he
slipped, he happened to go up to the roof and he slipped?
It sounds like these Rabbis were willing to commit suicide rather than
transgress, which raises really important halakhic, theological questions about when it’s a
case of יהרג ואל יעבור, Yehareg ve’al ya’avor, that somebody is saying
that I’ll kill you unless you do X, but you don’t have
any way out of doing X unless you actually take your own
life. And that was a big thing that came up in the
Crusades, and the אשכנזי Ashkenazi ראשונים Rishonim felt or at least in
hindsight rationalized or justified what was done, which was by saying that
you are allowed to take your own life. Anyway, that certainly seems
to be the message here. במיני עריות, Beminei arayot, in other words,
you know, is it, well, with a non-Jewish woman... okay, so that’s
an interesting... I don’t know if she’s married or not. Right. Well,
well the married would be, would be less relevant there. There is
an interesting debate in the ראשונים Rishonim whether it's גילוי עריות, Giluy
Arayot, sex with a non-Jewish woman, whether that falls into the גילוי
עריות Giluy Arayot category. According to this, it would seem like it
is. Right, if you read all of this הלכתית, Halakhically, but it
seems that part of the way to read this, and that also,
you know, gets to the question I raised about תוספות Tosafot and
martyrdom and whatever, is to read this as some type of heroic
act, you know, this what makes him so amazing and heroic, is
that normally this would not be like expected of a normal person,
either because it wouldn't technically be גילוי עריות Giluy Arayot or because
it would like be, what do you call it? You don't take
your own life regardless, right? But this is, but this is seen
as some heroic act. Okay, so anyway, there he was falling from
the roof, אליהו קבליה Eliyahu kablei and אליהו Eliyahu flew in and
caught him in mid-air. Okay, so אמר ליה, amar lei, so אליהו
Eliyahu said to him, אטרחתן ארבע מאה פרסה, atrachtan arba mea parsa,
you made me schlepp here, I was 400 miles away. And it's
sort of like, you know, it's like an Aladdin type of a
thing, you know, you made me fly here, what? Like Superman? Superman.
No. Okay, anyway, you made me fly here to catch you. אמר
ליה, amar lei, מי גרים לי? mi garim li? What made, what
what brought this about to me? לאו עניותא? lav aniyuta? It's because
I'm poor and I have to sell wicker baskets and I have
all these women coming to my store, so that exposed me to
this risk, you know, so don't blame me, what what choice did
I have? So יהב ליה שיפא דדינרי. yahav lei shifa de-dinari. He
said, okay, and he gave him a basket full of gold coins.
So you see that he was rewarded. Now, what does this by
the way have to do with the פסוק pasuk other than גבורי
כח? giborei koach? It could just be גבורי כח עושי דברו giborei
koach osei devaro when people actually need to gird strength and they
need to, you know, sort of resist and find that inner fortitude,
but also it's interesting, and I and I sort of noted the
fact that the פסוק pasuk here says לשמוע בקול דברו lishmoa be-kol
devaro after עושי דברו, osei devaro, which is a little ironic. First
you listen, then you do. What does it mean you do and
then you listen? So the מהרש"א Maharsha says that that's what the
דיוק diyuk is about, and that לשמוע בקול דברו lishmoa be-kol devaro
actually here is God. If you're גבורי כח עושי דברו giborei koach
osei devaro doing God's work, then God is לשמוע בקול דברו, lishmoa
be-kol devaro, God hears your, you know, word and therefore God comes
to save these rabbis who had the fortitude and the to believe
in God and to be willing to risk their lives. That's the
way the מהרש"א Maharsha reads it. You know, I sort of was
reading, the way I was reading it was to say, you know,
it's not just enough to do, it's to deeply like hear, to
connect deeply to sort of the, you know, the moral and religious
imperative. So beyond just the doing, and that gives you the strength,
you know, to do these type of heroic things when it's demanded.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara goes back.
Okay, that was the issue about passive versus active, sort of doing
like passive not resisting is like an act of an act of
a מצוה. mitzvah. But now we get back to reaping the rewards
in this world. So let's take a look. רמי ליה רבא לרב
נחמן. rami lei Rava le-Rav Nachman. רבא Rava showed a contradiction to
רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. תנן, tenan, אלו דברים שאדם עושה אותם ואוכל
פירותיהם בעולם הזה והקרן קיימת לו לעולם הבא, eilu devarim she-adam oseh
otam ve-okhel peroteihem ba-olam ha-zeh ve-ha-keren kayemet lo la-olam ha-ba, back to
the משנה Mishnah in פאה. Pe'ah. אלו הן כיבוד אב ואם וגמילות
חסדים והבאת שלום בין אדם לחברו ותלמוד תורה כנגד כולם. eilu hen
kibbud av va-em u-gemilut chasadim ve-hava'at shalom bein adam le-chavero ve-talmud torah
keneged kulam. Okay, those five. Now, בכיבוד אב ואם כתיב, be-kibbud av
va-em ketiv, now we're going to give the פסוקים. pesukim. By כיבוד
אב ואם kibbud av va-em it says, למען יאריכון ימיך ולמען ייטב
לך, lema'an yaarichun yamecha u-lema'an yitav lach, so that's why you see
it's good for you in this world, okay, reading it not like
רבי יעקב. Rabbi Yaakov. גמילות חסדים כתיב, gemilut chasadim ketiv, by
acts of kindness it says, רודף צדקה וחסד ימצא חיים צדקה וכבוד,
rodef tzedakah va-chesed yimtza chayim tzedakah ve-khavod,
so somebody who runs after, you know, righteousness or good deeds and
kindness will find life and righteousness and honor. So that clearly is
referring to this world, at least, you know, I mean again you
could interpret all this world to come, but פשט peshat is this
world. Right, right, ובהבאת שלום כתיב, u-ve-hava'at shalom ketiv, bringing peace, בקש
שלום ורדפהו. bakesh shalom ve-rodfehu.
One who seeks out peace and runs after it. ואמר רבי אבהו,
ve-amar Rabbi Abbahu, אתיא רדיפה רדיפה, atya redifah redifah, we make a
גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. כתיב הכא בקש שלום ורדפהו וכתיב התם רודף
צדקה וחסד. ketiv hacha bakesh shalom ve-rodfehu u-khetiv hatam rodef tzedakah va-chesed.
So we have all those פסוקים pesukim that show you that if
you do these things you get reward in this world.
ותלמוד תורה כתיב, ve-talmud torah ketiv, כי היא חייך ואורך ימיך, ki
hi chayecha ve-orech yamecha, it is your life and the length of
your days. So we get why all these things are in the
משנה Mishnah in פאה. Pe'ah. But here's my question, that's not an
exhaustive list. Okay, it says, how about בשילוח הקן נמי כתיב, be-shiluach
ha-ken nami ketiv, למען ייטב לך והארכת ימים lema'an yitav lach ve-ha'arachta
yamim as we saw just yesterday? וליתני נמי האי, ve-leisni nami hai,
why not list sending away the mother bird? So גמרא Gemara says
תנא ושייר, tana ve-shayer, yeah, it's an incomplete list. So גמרא Gemara
so he says back, תני תנא אלו דברים, tani tana eilu devarim,
it says these are the things, ואת אמרת תנא ושייר? ve-at amrat
tana ve-shayer? It's not a complete list? It sounds very much like
it is a complete list. So אמר רבא, amar Rava, רב אידי
אסברא לי. Rav Idi asbara li. רב אידי Rav Idi explained it
to me, here's what why the list was chosen. It's a particular
type of things that are being chosen and it's based on the
following דרשה derashah in the פסוק: pasuk: אמרו צדיק כי טוב, imru
tzadik ki tov, say to the righteous that it is good, כי
פרי מעלליהם יאכלו, ki peri ma'alaleihem yokhelu, that they will eat the
fruit of their deeds. So that's talking about reaping the fruit of
your good deeds in this world, but it's focusing on צדיק כי
טוב, tzadik ki tov, righteous because it is good. And this is
a very important גמרא Gemara sort of theologically or religiously that talks
about the difference between righteous and good, and what it means to
be a righteous person and what it means to be a good
person and. righteous person, he's good, or something about? No, certainly he
is good, or his acts are good. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says,
it reads it anyway as describing the person. So what type of
a righteous person reaps the benefit, the merit of their acts, the
reward of their acts in this world? צדיק כי טוב. Tzadik Ki
Tov. So he says, וכי יש צדיק טוב ויש צדיק שאינו טוב?
vechi yesh tzadik tov veyesh tzadik she'eino tov? Is there a צדיק
tzadik who's טוב tov and a צדיק tzadik who's not
טוב? tov? אלא טוב לשמים ולבריות זהו צדיק טוב. ela tov lashamayim
velabriyot zehu tzadik tov. Somebody who is good to God and good
to his fellow human being is a צדיק tzadik who is good.
טוב לשמים ורע לבריות, tov lashamayim vera labriyot, but if somebody is
good to God, is very good on the ritual מצוות, mitzvot, okay,
but is not at all good to his fellow person, fellow man,
זהו צדיק שאינו טוב. zehu tzadik she'eino tov. That is a צדיק
tzadik who is not good. Now, which is really sort of labels,
right, the idea that what we would sort of call, one way
to frame this is of course ethics and religion. And also, of
course, it's exactly the fallacy that people fall into, that they think
to be פרום frum only translates in the religious realm and not
in the moral realm, right? So the גמרא, Gemara, I don't know
whether it's helpful or not helpful this way, because it sort of
labels it, but you could say, oh it labels it, so I
could still be a צדיק, tzadik, I'm just not טוב, tov, but
I'm still a צדיק. tzadik. You know, you could sort of read
it that way that it legitimates the idea of being able to
be a צדיק tzadik without being טוב. tov. But it's more recognizing
a perception and a phenomenon and calling it out. And saying, you
know, sort of sort of saying that there's a real problem. You
know, you might sort of be religiously righteous, but fundamentally you're not
a good person, and you know, you're morally corrupt. So the point
is, which are the righteous that we want to focus on that
reap their rewards in this world? The people that are right, that
their righteous deeds, and here's how it answers the previous questions. We
want to focus on righteous deeds that are righteous and good deeds,
not just righteous deeds. So therefore the list of, you know, כיבוד
אב ואם kibbud av va'em and גמילות חסדים gemilut chasadim and that
list, those were not... שלוח הקן shiluach hakan is just doing God's
will. It's not about interpersonal. Okay, so it's true that you get,
you reap rewards in this world for sending away the mother bird?
Yes. But that wasn't the list we were interested in. We were
interested in the list of somebody who is really doing grea... is
a צדיק כי טוב. tzadik ki tov. That's a different category. Now,
you could say that person gets... now you could say, well I
don't know, you could say they get more of their rewards, they
get more dividends, or what I would like to say, and I
said yesterday, is that the rewards are not just that God is
rewarding you. Because the טוב tov is that you create goodness in
this world, and by the way, that's another way of reading טוב
tov here, is not just morally good, but that you actually create
goodness in this world. So if your צדקות tzidkus is a צדקות
tzidkus of goodness in this world, then that will actually concretely create
a better world in which you will reap the rewards of having
done those good deeds because of the real people you impact and
the realities that you create. So the point is, are there is
there righteous acts that are just between person and God that you
get rewarded for in this world? Yes, but that's not really the
message we're talking about and the point we want to emphasize. We
want to emphasize the creating good in this world, the צדיק כי
טוב. tzadik ki tov. And the end of the
דרשה drasha is כיוצא בדבר אתה אומר, kiyotzei badavar atah omer, אוי
לרשע רע, oi larasha ra, woe to the evil wicked person. כי
גמול ידיו יעשה לו, ki gemul yadav ye'aseh lo, he will be
paid back with the, you know, but
you know, accordance right with his deeds. וכי יש רשע רע ויש
שאינו רע? vechi yesh rasha ra veyesh she'eino ra? Is there a
wicked person who's evil and one that isn't evil? Yes. אלא רע
לשמים ולבריות הוא רשע רע. ela ra lashamayim velabriyot hu rasha ra.
Somebody who sins against God and against human beings, that is a
bad wicked person. רע לשמים ואינו רע לבריות, ra lashamayim ve'eino ra
labriyot, but if somebody sins against God but actually is a good
person, זה רשע שאינו רע. zeh rasha she'eino ra. גמרא Gemara says,
you know, you don't have a word like צדיק, tzadik, like רשע
rasha implies morally bad as well. I'm wondering if the sinful maybe
would be a good way of saying it, right? So a sinner,
you could have a good sinner, okay, and you could have I
guess an evil sa... a bad saint, okay. So anyway, although we
use saint also, some of these words often come in the English
language with the moral sense as well. But maybe anyway that's the
sense, you know, a transgressor. You could have a good transgressor because
he's good to people even though he transgresses against God. Okay, now
got to keep on moving. הזכות יש לה קרן ויש לה פירות.
hazechut yesh la keren veyesh la perot. Now we're going on with
a תוספתא Tosefta in פאה Pe'ah that develops this theme and now
contrasts the difference between good deeds and bad deeds. Good deeds are
always rewarded in a much higher degree to which bad deeds are
punished, okay. So הזכות hazechut merit, good deed, יש לה קרן, yesh
la keren, you deposit the principal in the bank for עולם הבא,
olam haba, ויש לה פירות, veyesh la perot, and you reap the
dividends and the rewards in this world, שנאמר אמרו צדיק כי טוב
כי פרי מעלליהם יאכלו. shene'emar imru tzadik ki tov ki pri ma'alehem
yocheilu. עבירה aveirah sins, יש לה קרן, yesh la keren, is only
paid back for the you only get the principal,
יש לה קרן, yesh la keren, ואין לה פירות, ve'ein la perot,
you don't suffer
beyond what you deserve for your sin, שנאמר אוי לרשע רע shene'emar
oi larasha ra כי פרי מעל... ki pri ma'al... כי גמול ידיו
ki gemul yadav excuse me יעשה לו. ye'aseh lo. לו. lo. By
the צדיק tzadik it was פרי מעלליהם, pri ma'alehem, the fruit, the
fruits of your labor means something more than what you did. Your
thing bears fruit, bears dividends. The רשע rasha only gets גמול
ידיו, gmul yadav, pay back what for himself, but the kids may
be different, right? Oh, I don't want to talk about that. Okay,
he only gets paid back equal to what he has done.
ואלמני מקיים v'almani m'kayem ויאכלו מפרי דרכם וממועצותיהם ישבעו, v'yochlu mipri darkam
umimootzoseihem yisbe'u, but I have another פסוק pasuk that speaks about the
fruit by a רשע. rasha. They will eat from the fruits of
their paths and from their, you know, scheming or whatever, you know,
they will, they will be sated, but meaning that they'll be paid
back not just with the principal, but beyond the principal. This is
with a רשע. rasha. So the גמרא Gemara says עבירה שעושה פירות
יש לה פירות. aveira she'osa peiros yesh la peiros. If the sin
brings forth fruit and has a real-world impact beyond just sinning to
God, similar to the discussion before about צדיק כי טוב, tzadik ki
tov, it's not just a sin, but it actually hurts people and
creates fruit, you know, or has a ripple effect, then יש לה
פירות, yesh la peiros, the person will suffer for the other impact
that that sin has had. ושאינה עושה פירות, v'she'eina osa peiros, if
it's sort of limited to the sin and doesn't go beyond that,
אין לה פירות, ein la peiros, then you only get punished for
the sin itself. Okay, now רשי Rashi also explains, I sort of
explained in terms of hurting other people, creating bad in this world,
but רשי Rashi also says if a person sins and that leads
other people to sin, right, like oh, well if he didn't keep
שבת, Shabbos, I don't have to keep שבת. Shabbos. Okay, but the
point is if it has a this-world type of an impact, and
that's a nice parallel to the גמילות חסדים, gmilus chasadim, right, when
your מצוות mitzvos have a this-world positive impact, then you reap a
real reward beyond the מצוה. mitzvah. And when your עבירות aveiros have
a real-world negative impact, then you'll reap the punishment beyond just the
עבירה aveira itself. Okay, now it says like
this, goes on, מחשבה טובה machshava tova with this comparison about good
and bad, מחשבה טובה מצרפה למעשה. machshava tova mitzarfah l'ma'aseh. A good
thought God gives you credit as if you did it. שנאמר she'ne'emar
אז נדברו יראי השם איש אל רעהו ויקשב השם וישמע ויכתב ספר
זיכרון לפניו ליראי השם ולחושבי שמו. az nidbru yirei Hashem ish el
re'ehu vayakshev Hashem vayishma vayikasev sefer zikaron lifanav liyirei Hashem ulchoshvei shmo.
They were just talking, and God listens and writes it down and
ולחושבי שמו, ulchoshvei shmo, for maybe like he's מחשב m'chashev it, that
means that they're thinking about God's name, anyway, he gives them credit.
So מאי ולחושבי שמו? mai ulchoshvei shmo? And now the גמרא Gemara
emphasizes, what does it mean to those who think about God's name?
אמר רב אסי, amar Rav Assi, אפילו חשב אדם לעשות מצוה ונאנס,
afilu chashav adam la'asos mitzvah v'ne'enas, even just thinking about doing a
מצוה, mitzvah, if you were, if it was, if the opportunity was
taken away from you, ולא עשה, v'lo asah, and you didn't do
it, מעלה עליו הכתוב כאילו עשה, ma'aleh alav hakatuv k'ilu asah, it's
like you get credit like you did. Now I want to point
out that it does say נאנס. ne'enas. It doesn't say you thought
about doing a מצוה mitzvah and then you thought better of it.
Okay, oh, I really want to go learn Torah, no, you know
what, there's a good movie on today, or whatever, that's not, you
don't get credit in that case. The credit is you really tried
and then somehow, you know, unexpected circumstances made it impossible. But you
really did try. Then you get credit. מחשבה רעה, machshava ra'ah, a
bad thought, plan, not just thought, plan, אין הקדוש ברוך הוא מצרפה
למעשה. ein Hakadosh Baruch Hu mitzarfah l'ma'aseh. God does not make it
like you've done it. שנאמר she'ne'emar און אם ראיתי בליבי לא ישמע
השם. avon im ra'isi belibi lo yishma Hashem. If I see sin
in my heart, God won't listen. God doesn't punish me for that.
ואלמני מקיים v'almani m'kayem הנני מביא אל העם הזה רעה פרי מחשבותם,
hineni meivi el ha'am hazeh ra'ah pri machshavosam, I will bring evil
to this people the fruit of their thoughts, okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says like before, מחשבה שעושה פרי, machshava she'osa pri,
again paying on the fruit of their thoughts, if the fruit bears,
if the thought bears fruit, what would it mean for the thought
to bear fruit? What would that thought, evil thought, bear fruit? It
would become an action. So if the thought leads to an action,
then you get punished for the thought as well. Okay,
so מחשבה שעושה פרי הקדוש ברוך הוא מצרפה למעשה. machshava she'osa pri
Hakadosh Baruch Hu mitzarfah l'ma'aseh. If it produces an action, then you
get punished for the thought as well. מחשבה שאין בה פרי, machshava
she'ein bah pri, if it doesn't produce an action, אין הקדוש ברוך
הוא מצרפה למעשה, ein Hakadosh Baruch Hu mitzarfah l'ma'aseh, you don't get
punished. ואלא הא דכתיב v'ela ha d'chtiv למען תפוס את בית ישראל
בליבם, l'ma'an tfos es beis Yisrael belibam, to seize בני ישראל Bnei
Yisrael for in for the thoughts of their hearts? So that sounds
like they are punished. אמר רב אחא בר יעקב, amar Rav Acha
bar Yaakov, הוא בעבודה זרה הוא דכתיב. hu b'avoda zara hu d'chtiv.
No, no, that's עבודה זרה. avoda zara. דאמר מר, d'amar mar, חמורה
עבודה זרה כנגד כל המצוות שכל הכופר בה כמודה בכל התורה כולה,
chamura avoda zara k'neged kol hamitzvos shekol hakofir bah k'modeh b'chol haTorah
kulah, that anybody who rejects עבודה זרה avoda zara is like who,
who accepts the entire תורה, Torah, similarly anybody who believes in עבודה
זרה avoda zara is like they reject the תורה. Torah. So one
wonders also is the point here that it's just so weighty that
it's so taboo that even to be thinking about it you deserve
to be punished, like we don't even want people to be thinking
about it, it's just so off-limits, or is part of the point,
you know, sort of the way the רמבם Rambam would have it,
it's more about less about the act of עבודה זרה avoda zara
and more about the, the, you know, fate, the heresy of faith?
Right, if you're thinking about it, there's a stepping away from God
in the very considering of the act. So there's an element of,
you know, עבודה זרה avoda zara is not just the act, part
of עבודה זרה avoda zara is very much the thought that accompanies
the act. So what does that thought mean without the act, right?
So, so it could be that that's part of what's going on
here. Now it says like this, הוא אמר כדרב הונא. hu amar
k'de'Rav Huna. That's רב הונא, Rav Huna, דאמר רב הונא, d'amar Rav
Huna, there's when you get punished for your, for your plan to
sin even without sinning. Like רב הונא Rav Huna says. דאמר רב
הונא d'amar Rav Huna כיון שאדם עבר עבירה ושנה בה הותרה לו.
keivan she'adam avar aveirah ve'shanah bah hutra lo. If a person does
a sin and he repeats it, it becomes, it's permitted to him.
הותרה לו סלקא דעתך? hutra lo salka da'atakh? Really? It becomes permitted
once he's done it twice? אלא נעשית לו כהיתר. ela na'aseit lo
k'heter. It becomes in your eyes like it's permissible. So once a
person has repeated sinful action, then even the thought is essentially going
to be, that thought will easily translate into action at this stage
because now the person does not feel that the thing is off-limits
or taboo anymore. And therefore, the person will get punished just for
planning it because it's sort of assumed like
at this stage if you're planning it, you're probably going to do
it. And if you didn't do it, as רש״י Rashi says, it's
probably just because you lost, you didn't have the opportunity. Once somebody
has gone to McDonald's twice, right? And then he's thinking, oh, maybe
I'll go to McDonald's today, and then he didn't wind up, it
was probably not for the right reason that he didn't go. There's
probably he didn't get a chance to go or whatever. At that
stage, it's sort of like
we don't give you credit for resisting. The fact that you were
planning is seen as most likely you will do it, and not
doing it is seen as it was by chance you didn't do
it. So you actually get punished for just the thought itself.
What? This is for all מצוות mitzvot as opposed to the ones
that we were talking about? Yeah, yeah, he's saying normally for bad,
for planning to do an עבירה aveirah you don't get punished for,
but if you're a repeated offender, then you get punished for just
the plan. Because the plan will easily, not עבודה זרה, avodah zarah,
סתם, stam, because the plan will easily translate into action. And the
זכות zechut part, before we were saying it was like just specific
ones, like for no, זכות zechut you get any מחשבה טובה machshavah
tovah you get credit as long as it was
נאנס. ne'enas. Okay. אמר רבי אבהו משום רבי חנינא: Amar Rabbi Abbahu
mishum Rabbi Chanina: נוח לו לאדם שיעבור עבירה בסתר ואל יחלל שם
שמים בפרהסיא. noach lo l'adam she'ya'avor aveirah b'seter v'al yechallel shem Shamayim
b'farhesya. So now that we're talking about sort of sinning, we're talking
and also maybe this plays up before about the עושה פרי oseh
pri and not עושה פרי, oseh pri, how are other people impacted
by your sins? So he says if somebody has to do an
עבירה, aveirah, better to do it in private and not cause a
חילול השם. chillul Hashem. And the idea of not just cause a
חילול השם, chillul Hashem, the חילול השם chillul Hashem could be a
disgrace. Ah, I can't believe that a פרום frum Jew is doing
this, right? And that's better to do one עבירה aveirah than two
עבירות. aveirot. But it could also be that the חילול השם chillul
Hashem is that then it's עושה פרי, oseh pri, that it leads
to actually impacting other people. Okay. שנאמר ואתם בית ישראל כה אמר
ה׳ איש גלוליו לכו עבדו ואחר אם אינכם שומעים אלי ואת שם
קדשי לא תחללו. she'ne'emar v'atem beit Yisrael koh amar Hashem ish gilulav
lechu avodu v'achar im einchem shome'im elai v'et shem kodshi lo techallalu.
Go take your idols and worship them if you are not listening
to me,
but do not desecrate My name. If you're going to sin, sin,
but don't do it with desecrating My name. אמר רב עלאי הזקן,
Amar Rav Ilai HaZaken, and by the way, that also could be
playing off the idea of נעשית לו כהיתר na'aseit lo k'heter that
if it's like a היתר, heter, you won't be as sensitive to
doing it in public or doing it in private. And here it's
trying to say, if you're going to sin, at least be sensitive
to these other issues. Maintain that sensitivity that it is a sin,
the way it can impact other people. At least do it in
private. Okay, now the funny thing is about that is that you
might think, as the גמרא Gemara is going to say, that doing
it in private creates a sort of becomes theological, it creates like
a hypocrisy and like there's a theological problem. So that's what the
גמרא Gemara is going to say. אמר רב עלאי הזקן: Amar Rav
Ilai HaZaken: אם רואה אדם שיצרו מתגבר עליו, im ro'eh adam she'yitzro
mitgaber alav, if somebody sees that, well first we have this other
teaching, if somebody sees that their יצר הרע yeitzer hara is having
the power over them, as opposed to before when we talked about
resisting your
יצר הרע, yeitzer hara, ילך למקום שאין מכירים אותו, yeilech l'makom she'ein
makirim oto, go to a place that you're not
recognized, that they don't recognize you, וילבש שחורים ויתכסה שחורים, v'yilbash shechorim
v'yitkaseh shechorim, and dress in black and cover yourself in like mourning
clothes or in black
clothes, ויעשה מה שלבו חפץ, v'ya'aseh mah she'libo chafetz, and go ahead,
if you have to sin, then you'll sin, ואל יחלל שם שמים
בפרהסיא, v'al yechallel shem Shamayim b'farhesya, but you will not desecrate God's
name in public. So רש״י Rashi says the fact that they don't
recognize you, and apparently somebody dressed in black, people keep their distance
from, they assume he's mourning, or they assume that they're somehow he's
on the margins of society, it'll allow you to remain anonymous. Okay?
And therefore you'll sin, but you'll sin in an anonymous way, and
at least you won't be מחלל שם שמים. mechallel shem Shamayim. Now
the ראשונים Rishonim were deeply bothered by this because in a way,
it's no different than what we said before. But it is practical
advice, and practical advice linked with יעשה מה שלבו חפץ, ya'aseh mah
she'libo chafetz, do what your heart desires, sounds like it's giving license.
Okay? So a number of ראשונים, Rishonim, רש״י Rashi a little bit
throws in another point, hopefully this, through this process and dressing yourself
in black and covering yourself in black or whatever, hopefully that'll change
what your heart desires. Your heart, yeah, I know, it's תוספות Tosafot
quoting רבינו חננאל, Rabbeinu Chananel, but it was already in רש״י. Rashi.
Therefore, your heart won't desire it as much, but God forbid, nobody
is giving you license to do it. Okay, but the פשט pshat
is not that way, right? The פשט pshat is again not that
you have license, you're still sinning, but what we're saying is that
if you're going to sin anyway, better to sin in this way.
Of course, the problem is, is that how do you determine that?
Like maybe if you didn't give me this option and I had
to sin in a way that people would see me, that would
actually stop me from sinning. Right? So like רב משה Rav Moshe
was once asked a question about, I think it was just about
a guy going into the movie theater, I think one time I
saw it was about a guy going into a certain type of
a movie theater, but I think at In rereading the תשובה, t'shuvah,
it was just about going into a movie theater, which apparently was
a sin enough in itself. Anyway, the question was, should I take
off my ירמולקה yarmulke or not take off my ירמולקה, yarmulke, right?
Which is an interesting question. Like if I take off my ירמולקה,
yarmulke, I'm not מחלל שם שמים, m'chalel shem shamayim, whatever the thing
was that was seen as the חילול השם, chillul Hashem, but then
maybe I'll feel that'll give me more license to do it again,
right? On the other hand, if I keep my ירמולקה yarmulke on,
maybe it'll stop me from doing it, but maybe it'll make me
feel comfortable with doing it even though I am presenting myself. You
know, so it really raises very... I think he's... I don't know,
I don't remember what he said. I have to go check. Anyway,
okay, so keeping your ירמולקה yarmulke on be to keep the connection
with השם Hashem strong or because of what other people think about
you? No, to show to others... right, well that was exactly the
question, like how much... I mean those are exactly the questions that
were being raised. So anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says like this,
איני, eini, is this really true? והתניא, ve-hatanya, כל שלא חס על
כבוד קונו, kol shelo chas al kavod kono, ראוי לו שלא בא
לעולם. ra'uy lo shelo ba la-olam. Anybody who does not concern with
God's honor is not deserving of coming into the world. מאי היא,
mai hi, and what is that? רבא אמר, Rava amar, זה המסתכל
בקשת, zeh ha-mistakel ba-keshet, looking directly at the rainbow, and that has
to do with Kabbalistic issues, which I won't get into. רב יוסף
אמר, Rav Yosef amar, you're not... you haven't been learning with me
for 40 years yet. Okay, רב יוסף אמר, Rav Yosef amar, זה
העובר עבירה בסתר, zeh ha-over aveira be-seter, if you do a sin
in private, because then it's showing that you think that God can't
see you in private or that what you're demonstrating is that you're
more concerned with how people perceive you than with how God perceives
you. So there's a theological problem of sinning in private. Okay, but
it's... but there's a practical reason why it's necessary, because whatever that
does to your own faith issues or demonstrates, at least it protects
other people from the bad effects of your sin. So the גמרא
Gemara says, לא קשיא. lo kashya. So how... הא דמצי כייף ליה
ליצריה והא דלא מצי כייף ליה ליצריה. ha de-matsi kayif lei le-yitzrei
ve-ha de-la matsi kayif lei le-yitzrei. The difference is, can you get...
will you have the power to overcome your יצר הרע? yeitzer hara?
If you have the power to overcome your יצר הרע yeitzer hara
and you could stop yourself from doing it, and then you're choosing
to do it in private, what you're actually doing is then the
doing it in private becomes what is the license, what's allowing you
to sin. Like, I... I have an ability not to do it,
but you know what? I'll just go ahead and do it in
private, nobody will see me. So then it sort of demonstrates the
fact that you don't think God sees you, you're more concerned with
people or whatever, you could stop yourself from doing it. In that
case, doing it in private is actually a... it's a theological sin,
that is what is giving you the license. If you know that
you can't stop yourself and you're going to do it anyway, then
you might as well do it in a way that doesn't create
as much of a חילול השם. chillul Hashem. The question is, most
of the time we don't know. And most of the time the
choices that we're making impact whether we are able to or whether
we're going to do it again or so on. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara says like this, תנן התם, tenan hatam, we taught over
there, אין מקיפין בחילול השם, ein makifin be-chillul Hashem, אחד שוגג ואחד
מזיד. echad shogeg ve-echad mezid. Whether you're שוגג shogeg or מזיד, mezid,
we are not מקיף makif when it comes to חילול השם. chillul
Hashem. What does מקיף makif mean? מאי אין מקיפין? mai ein makifin?
אמר מר זוטרא, Amar Mar Zutra, שאין עושים כחנווני. she-ein osim ke-chanvani.
You don't... it doesn't get put on credit. הקפה hakafa is credit.
God doesn't... God will punish you immediately for חילול השם. chillul Hashem.
מר בריה דרבינא אמר, Mar berei de-Ravina amar, לומר שאם היתה שקולה
מכרעת. lomar she-im hayta shekula machra'at. Now מקיפין makifin means, Rashi says
it means like to balance, so if חילול השם chillul Hashem is
on the balance side, on the negative side of the equation, then
even your 50/50 but it includes חילול השם, chillul Hashem, that's not
50/50. Then you're... then you're in the demerits. Then you're the... you
know, so... so that does not get balanced out by other things.
Okay, תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. So מקיפין makifin means that there aren't...
we don't have mitzvah points that accumulate and subtract? Something like that.
תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, לעולם יראה אדם עצמו כאילו חציו חייב וחציו
זכאי. le'olam yir'eh adam atzmo ke-ilu chetzyo chayav ve-chetzyo zakai. So we
are once again repeating because we just had this scene about tipping
the scales. Fascinating how much the גמרא Gemara focuses on this, because
one would think like, you know, like... whatever, anyway we'll talk about
it. But a person should always see themselves as half... half, you
know, sinful and half mer... or half
deserving of punishment and half meritorious. עשה מצוה אחת אשריו, asa mitzvah
achat ashrav, doing one mitzvah praised are you, שהכריע עצמו לכף זכות,
she-hichria atzmo le-chaf zechut, that you tip the scales into the merit.
עבר עבירה אחת אוי לו, avar aveira achat oy lo, if you
do one sin woe to you, שהכריע עצמו לכף חובה, she-hichria atzmo
le-chaf chova, you tip the scales into the... into the deserving of
punishment, into, you know, שנאמר, she-ne'emar, as it says, וחוטא אחד יאבד
טובה הרבה. ve-chotei echad ye'aved tova harbe. One sinner or one sin
is being read will lose great good. בשביל חטא יחידי שחטא אובד
ממנו טובות הרבה. Bishvil cheit yechidi she-chata oved mimenu tovot harbe.
Just one sin you do, you lose all of the good deeds?
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Elazar be-Rabbi Shimon amar, לפי שהעולם
נידון אחר רובו, lefi she-ha-olam nidon achar rubo, yes, because the world
is judged based on the majority. והיחיד נידון אחר רובו, ve-ha-yachid nidon
achar rubo, and the person is judged based on their majority, the
totality. Are they basically a good person or bad person? Is the
world basically deserving or undeserving? Okay, so... so עשה מצוה אחת, asa
mitzvah achat, so sometimes doing just one mitzvah, אשריו, ashrav, praise are
you, שהכריע את עצמו ואת כל העולם לכף זכות. she-hichria et atzmo
ve-et kol ha-olam le-chaf zechut. You bring the entire... you bring yourself
and the whole world, because not only should you see yourself as
50/50, you should see the whole world as 50/50. So when you
tip... it's like right now in the election season, right? You know,
you tip one... Breezy tips one state, tips the whole election. Okay,
all based on your
vote. Yes, now no that wasn't I should've read that in a
slightly different way. בשביל חטא יחידי שעשה זה איבד ממנו ומכל העולם
טובה הרבה. bishvil cheit yechidi she'asah zeh ibeid mimeno u'mikol ha'olam tovah
harbeh.
Yes, you can bring the whole world down with you. רבי שמעון
בן יוחאי אומר, Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai omer, אפילו afilu I want
to get back to that, but let's just finish for the משנה
Mishnah first. אפילו צדיק גמור כל ימיו, afilu tzaddik gamur kol yamav,
even if somebody's righteous their whole day, ומרד באחרונה, u'marad b'acharonah, and
he rebels in his last day, איבד את הראשונות, ibeid et harishonot,
he loses all the good stuff, שנאמר צדקת הצדיק לא תצילנו ביום
פשעו, she'ne'emar tzidkat hatzaddik lo tatzilenu b'yom pish'o, that the righteousness will
not save him on the day of his sin.
Okay, ואפילו רשע גמור כל ימיו, v'afilu rasha gamur kol yamav, and
even a רשע rasha at the last moment he does תשובה, teshuvah,
ועשה תשובה באחרונה, v'asah teshuvah b'acharonah, אין מזכירין לו שוב רשעו, ein
mazkirin lo shuv rish'o, it's not remembered for him his wickedness, שנאמר
ורשעת הרשע לא יכשל בה ביום שובו מרשעו, she'ne'emar v'rish'at harasha lo
yikashel bah b'yom shuvo me'rish'o, the wickedness he will not stumble over
it if he returns from his evil deeds. So now the גמרא
Gemara says, well, I don't know, the גמרא Gemara says anyway, so
the גמרא's Gemara bothered, right? Because and I'm bothered, because you would
say תשובה teshuvah we get. We want to say that תשובה teshuvah
is always there and to redeem you at the end, although you
could still ask, how does it help for all the lives you've
ruined? Okay, right exactly. But let's at least between sin so against
God, you want to think that תשובה teshuvah can help you, you
know, can ultimately, תשובה's teshuvah that's the power of תשובה. teshuvah. But
you would like to think that if somebody did righteous deeds their
whole lives, even if at the very last day they rebelled against
God, that they still have the righteous deeds that they've done, right?
You wouldn't think that it destroys everything. So that's the גמרא's Gemara
question. The גמרא Gemara says ונהוי כמחצה עונות ומחצה זכיות. v'nehevei k'mechtza
avonot u'mechtza zachuyot.
This righteous person that rebelled on his last day, let him at
least be like fifty-fifty. I mean, he's got 90 years of good
deeds, right? What is this last day? So that makes him a
wicked person? אמר ריש לקיש בתוהא על הראשונות. Amar Reish Lakish b'toheh
al harishonot. You're right. We say it become you lose all the
earlier credit if on that last day you sort of say, why
did I spend my entire life being such a good person? It
never paid. I should have just had a life of pleasure, etc.
So in that case, that's like the opposite of תשובה, teshuvah, if
you think about it. תשובה teshuvah is because you regret and therefore
your thought retroactively undoes the past, right? So here, you know, so
here your thought about you regret the good deeds undoes it. But
again the question about this, the same way the question about the
תשובה, teshuvah, is but what about all the people you helped? What
about all the תורה Torah you taught, right? What about all of
that? So personally, you know, fine, you know, maybe as a person
now you're a wicked person because you deny, you regret it all.
You know, but how about the deeds? The deeds still had their
real effect. You know, it's the same question with תשובה teshuvah and
I don't really have a good answer to that. Of course it
reminds me of the joke, which I can't tell because we don't
have enough time. Okay, I'll tell it. One quick sec. So the
guy's a צדיק tzaddik his whole life. Last day, he's 100 years
old, he's dying in bed, he's in the hospital, he calls for
a priest. So the priest comes in and he says, he says,
I want to convert. He says, you want to convert? He says,
you know,
Rabbi Frank, you've been a righteous person your whole life, you've done
תורה Torah and מצוות mitzvos and everything, says whatever, goes on and
on and on. You know, why is it that now, 100 years
old, you're on your... why do you want to convert? Says, better
one of them should die.
Okay, I don't know if I should have told that, whatever. Anyway,
okay, so I want to say something though about the מחצה עבירות
mechtza aveiros and the מחצה זכיות. mechtza zachuyot. And I'm only slightly
kidding about its relevance, you know, in terms of like an election
season, right? Didn't they say that John Kennedy won only because of
one extra vote in each county in California? Like if you do
the math, if one vote had gone the other way in every
county in California, he would have lost California and lost the election.
Okay, so and so people say like, again I'm using the voting
model, what difference does my one vote make, right? But if everybody
thought that way, right, then whatever. You know, the point is that
yes, you know, your one vote can tip the scale and make
a difference if especially if everybody acts in that way. Thinking in
those terms, right, if you think in the big picture, it's like
what difference is it going to make? And therefore you're not motivated
to do the right thing and to go out and vote, right?
So similarly, you know, if thinking that always like I am half
righteous and half meritorious, otherwise people will like say, yeah, you know,
I've done so many עבירות aveiros in my life, what difference is
it going to make? Or they'll say the opposite, you know, I
got a lot of credit to my name, I spent a lot
of time doing מצוות mitzvos or whatever, I don't have to push
myself to do another מצוה, mitzvah, right? So sort of if you're
able to really see yourself in this way, it really is a
constant spur in recognizing the consequence and the weight still of every
good deed and of every bad deed. And you know, sometimes also
thinking about the world, like people that are activists for change, it's
like what difference is it going to make if I go ahead
and I buy organic eggs? Like that's going to change the reality?
Right? Of course if everybody said that, then nothing would change, right?
But if a lot of individuals sort of see that no, the
world is fifty-fifty and like. This little act might tip the scales
if, you know, enough people do that enough times or whatever, real
things really can change. So it's a very powerful way of thinking
and it really taps into our psychology that often leads to complacency.
All right, let's try to see if we can do in the
next four minutes, I don't know, maybe people will give me a
few extra minutes we can finish. Okay, last
משנה. mishna. כל שישנו במקרא ובמשנה ובדרך ארץ, Kol sheyeshno bemikra uvemishna
uvederech eretz, again the כל, kol, anybody, but now we're talking about
people, people who do מצוות. mitzvot. So anybody who is like, you
know, connected to, who learns
תורה, משנה, ודרך ארץ, Torah, Mishna, and Derech Eretz, presumably like a
פרנסה, parnassa, like engaged in, no, no, no, engaged in a profession,
in some type of a, you know, of some productive labor, לא
במהרה הוא חוטא, lo bimehera hu chote, does not sin quickly. I
think it's interesting to note the three, מקרא Mikra and משנה, Mishna,
right, because I think the point is you could just say it
means engaged in תורה Torah study, but it does mention them as
different things. And I think that like מקרא Mikra might be... משנה
Mishna is like הלכה. halacha. You know, משנה Mishna was, to quote
a Livny again, like apodictic teachings. It's true there are debates, right,
but it's bottom line, right, it's sort of telling you here's what
you do and so on. That's how you live your life. Okay,
that's sort of like more more הלכה. halacha. מקרא Mikra is connecting
you to God, right? מקרא Mikra is sort of like, you know,
the religious connection. So if you have this sort of religious engagement,
and this halachic engagement, and you actually are like, not, you know,
are work in the real world because work also hopefully keeps you
away from sin, but it also, you know, makes you sort of,
you know, sort of like appreciate the,
you know, what is it? It's anyway, whatever. I can't go now
just... Anyway, לא במהרה הוא חוטא. lo bimehera hu chote. Anyway, so
if you're both connected in a world of learning, but you're also
connected enough to the real world, right, so then that does not
lead to sin. שנאמר והחוט המשולש לא במהרה ינתק, Shene'emar vehachut hameshulash
lo bimehera yinatek, and the three-fold, you know, the three-twisted cord will
not break easily. וכל שאינו לא במקרא ולא במשנה ולא בדרך ארץ,
Vechol she'eino lo bemikra velo bemishna velo bederech eretz, if you're not
in presumably any of these, אינו מן היישוב, eino min hayishuv, you're
not really part of settled society. You're not connected to God, to
תורה, Torah, to הלכה, Halacha, to making the world a better place.
So so therefore anyway you're on the outskirts. אמר רבי אלעזר בר
צדוק, Amar Rabbi Elazar bar Tzadok, למה צדיקים נמשלים בעולם הזה לאילן,
lamma tzaddikim nimshalim baolam haze le'ilan, why are righteous people compared to
a tree? שכולו עומד במקום טהרה, Shekulo omed bemakom tahara, now they're
compared to a certain type of a tree. A tree that is
sort of planted in a pure place ונופו נוטה למקום טומאה venofo
note lemakom tumah and a little bit of the tree sticks into
a bad place, a place of טומאה. tumah. נקצץ נופו, Niktzatz nofo,
so you cut the branch that's sticking into the bad place, כולו
עומד במקום טהרה, kulo omed bemakom tahara, it all stands in the
good place. כך הקדוש ברוך הוא מביא יסורין על צדיקים בעולם הזה,
Kacha Hakadosh Baruch Hu mevi yissurin al tzaddikim baolam haze, God brings
the punishment to צדיקים tzaddikim in this world or suffering, כדי שיירשו
עולם הבא, kede sheyirshu olam haba, so they so they are able
to get to the real place where they belong. Their real place...
צדיקים tzaddikim are really planted in עולם הבא olam haba in a
place of תורה Torah and מצוות. mitzvot. That's where they belong. Anything
that moved into the other zone gets cut away. So they suffer
a little for that. שנאמר... Shene'emar... to cut it off. ראשיתך מצער,
Reshitcha mitzar, your beginning will be painful, ואחריתך ישגה מאד veachritcha yisge
me'od and in the end very successful. ולמה רשעים דומים בעולם הזה
לאילן... Velamma resha'im domim baolam haze le'ilan... and for what,
maybe it should be ולמה v'lamma רשעים דומים בעולם הזה לאילן. resha'im
domim baolam haze le'ilan. What are they compared to? לאילן שכולו עומד
במקום טומאה, Le'ilan shekulo omed bemakom tumah, a tree that's fully standing
in a place of טומאה tumah ונופו נוטה למקום טהרה, venofo note
lemakom tahara, and a little branch is going into a place of
a good place. But their basic anchoring in their roots are in
the bad place, are in גיהנום, Gehennom, in wickedness. So therefore the
little bit that goes into the wrong place, that has to be
cut away, that's not... does not reflect their essence. So נקצץ נופו,
niktzatz nofo, once you cut that branch כולו עומד במקום טומאה, kulo
omed bemakom tumah, they get back to where they really belong. כך
הקדוש ברוך הוא משפיע להם טובה לרשעים בעולם הזה, Kacha Hakadosh Baruch
Hu mashpia lahem tova leresha'im baolam haze, God gives them goodness in
this world כדי להורידם לדרגה תחתונה kede le'hordom le'darga tachtona in order
to bring them to the lowest levels of גיהנום. Gehennom. So like
you might think that's unjust, and he's telling you it's not unjust,
it's just a restoring them to where they really belong. שנאמר יש
דרך ישר לפני איש ואחריתה דרכי מות. Shene'emar yesh derech yashar lifne
ish ve'achrita darche mavet. It looks good but in the end it
ends to death. So that really has nothing to do with this
משנה. mishna. That probably really belonged to the previous גמרא, Gemara, you
know, what's connected to the previous משנה. mishna. Okay, now we really
turn to this משנה mishna about... this משנה mishna which talks about,
you know, מקרא, משנה, ודרך ארץ, Mikra, Mishna, and Derech Eretz, about
which connects in a way learning and doing, although דרך ארץ Derech
Eretz is not exactly doing מצוות, mitzvot, but still learning and doing.
And now we get, I'm so sad that we are already have
so... we've run out of time, but we get to what is
like such a big theological, practical question. So let's take a look.
Maybe we can do it tomorrow. Yeah, you know what? Even though
it would be nice to finish the פרק, perek, I think we're
going to stop here and we'll do this tomorrow.